Guide to the Stanford University, Department of Computer Science, Stanford Computer Forum Distinguished Lecture Series, Videorecordings V0058
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Department of Computer Science, Stanford Computer Forum Distinguished Lecture Series, videorecordings
1978-1998
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University. Computer Science Department
V0058
15.25 Linear Feet
Lectures by computer professionals and professors from Stanford and other universities presented to the Computer Systems Laboratory Seminar, the Department of Computer Science Colloquium, and other special events.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Administrative transfers, 1989, 1990, 2001, 2016.
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Description of the Collection
Lectures by computer professionals and professors from Stanford and other universities presented to the Computer Systems Laboratory Seminar, the Department of Computer Science Colloquium, and other special events.
Science -- History.; Videorecordings.; Computer engineering; Computers.; Computer programs.; Oren, Timothy.; Diaconis, Persi; Nishi, Yoshio.; Reid, Brian K.; Shoch, John F.; Hertzfeld, Andy.; Hoff, Ted.; Kildall, Gary A.; Miller, William F.; Bobrow, Daniel G. (Daniel Gureasko); Lenat, Douglas B.; Bechtolsheim, Andy.; Stanford University. Computer Science Department; Felsenstein, Lee.; Nishi, Yoshio.; Stanford University. Computer Science Department; Wirth, Niklaus.
- Videorecordings
  - Mainframe CPU Design with LSI and VLSI, by Dr. Gary Tjaden., 1978-11-08; V0058.002; 1 videotape(s) (u-matic) (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    A new design approach, called Multiple-Microinstruction- StreamlSingleMacroinstruction- Stream, has been shown to yield mainframe performance using offthe- shelf LSI modules. Design with VLSI does not lend itself to the use of off-theshelf modules, but a very orderly design, such as encouraged with this new approach, is required. This talk describes some of the more subtle aspects of designing with LSI and discusses the new considerations necessary for designing with VLSI.
  - Fibernet: Multimode Optical Fibers for Local Computer Networks, by Dr. Robert M. Metcalfe., 1978-12-06; V0058.003; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 1)
    Local computer networks which communicate over copper conductors have been developed both to promote resource sharing and provide increased performance. Such networks typically operate at bandwidth x length (Bw*L) products up to a few MHz*km. Here we consider the use of fiber optics in such networks, and give a status report on a star-configured fiber optic network experiment called Fibernet which operates at a B w*L product of -100 MHz*km at a data rate of 150 Mbits/s and which in its final phases with connect up to 19 stations. We compare the merits and problems for linear, ring and several star configurations, and of active versus passive networks.
  - Dataflow: Architecture and Language, by Prof. Charles S. Wetherell., 1979-04-18; V0058.004; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 1)
    Large scientific computations require not just greater throughput from computing systems, but also faster response time. The dataflow architecture with run faster by utilizing any army of cheap, slow, easily replicatable processing units. This novel design also forces some novelties into programming languages used on the dataflow machine. Particularly important are explicit exposure of parallel computations and the complete avoidance of side effects. The new architecture, the associated language, and the effects on scientific applications are all discussed.
  - A Proposed Standard for Floating-Point Arithmetic, by Dr. John Palmer., 1978-11-01; V0058.005; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 1)
    A standard for floating-point arithmetic is under serious consideration by an IEEE standards committee. INTEL has implemented a subset of the proposed standard in hardware and software. The proposed standard is explained along with some evaluation of its benefits and costs.
  - The Mu-Net: A Scalable Multiprocessor Architecture, by Prof. Stephen Ward., 1979-01-17; V0058.006; 1 videotape(s) (u-matic) (Box 1)
    A research program leading to tools and methodology for dealing with a wide spectrum of real-time computation requirements is described. Two major foci of this research are CONSORT, a very high-level programming language specialized to applications imposing hard real-time constraints, and the Mu-Net, a mUltiprocessor run-time system whose performance characteristics are transparently scalable over a wide range.
  - Design Tradeoffs of the VAX 111780, by Dr. David M. Plummer., 1979-02-14; V0058.007; 1 videotape(s) (u-matic) (Box 1)
    David Plummer provides an overview of the evolutionary design process involved in extending the PDPII into the VAX 111780. A number of the interesting architectural features of the machine were discussed within the context of compromises and tradeoffs in performance, cost and utility. These topics include the virtual memory system, variable length instruction formats, bit efficiency, uniform software interfaces and the distribution of architectural components to achieve better performance.
  - Intel 2920 Analog Microprocessor: Architecture and Applications by Dr. Ted Hoff., 1979-10-10; V0058.008; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 2)
    The 2920 is a single chip digital microprocessor which contains analog to digital and digital to analog conversion. This processor may be used to implement a variety of traditional analog functions such as modems, speech synthesizers and filter arrays.
  - The Motorola 68000 Microprocessor, by Dr. Edward Stritter., 1979-10-31; V0058.009; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 2)
    The semiconductor industry has translated advances in LSI technology into a new generation of very high performance microprocessors. One such processor is the Motorola 68000. This presentation discusses the 68000 from the points of view of the programmer, the system designer and the computer architect. The instruction set, register set and the bus structure is described. In addition, the implementation and internal structure of the chip is discussed, particularly in terms of performance goals and LSI technology constraints.
  - Secrets of High Performance Processor Design, by Dr. Thomas M. McWilliams., 1980-04-09; V0058.010; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 2)
    This talk reveals a number of major secrets central to the design of modem top-of-theline digital processors. It treats several of the basic techniques and circuits which performance-oriented designers currently use to realize maximum throughput implementations of a given architecture, and discusses the impact of several common architectural features on the design of very high performance machines. The throughput-enhancing techniques used in the designs of the S-1 Mark I and Mark IIA processors are used extensively as illustrations of these design principles and practices.
  - An Implementation of PLII Subset G for Limited Resource Computers, by Dr. Gary A. Kildall., 1980-04-16; V0058.011; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 2)
    PLII-80 is an application language for microprocessor based computers which use the CP/M. operating system, and is based upon the new ANS PLII General Purpose Subset, called Subset G. The subset includes the more significant application oriented features, while eliminated the seldom-used or redundant constructs. the resulting language is simpler to learn, more consistent in form, and easier to compile. The PLII- 80 translator, discussed here, is a three pass optimizing compiler which operates under CP/M. in a 38 kilobyte area. the significant features of Subset G are presented, along with a number of implementation techniques used to reduce memory requirements while providing a measure of code improvement during the code generation phase
  - Execute Only Program Memories by Dr. Marc T. Kaufman., 1980-05-17; V0058.012; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 2)
    A new technique has been developed that allows computer programs to be protected from copying, while still allowing them to be executed. The method is applicable to general purpose computers, including hobby computers.
  - Experience with an Applicative String Processing Language, Dr. James Morris., 1980-05-28; V0058.013; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 2)
    Experience using and implementing the language Poplar is described. The major conclusions are: applicative programming can be made more natural through the use of built-in iterative operators and post-fix notation. Clever evaluation strategies, such as lazy evaluation, can make applicative programming more computations efficient. Patte:n matching can be performed in an applicative framework. Many problems remaIn.
  - Architecture of the MIT LISP Machine, by Thomas F. Knight., 1980-11-12; V0058.014; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 3)
    The LISP machine is a general purpose emulation engine tailored to the execution of compiled LISP. It was designed in 1975 as the hardware basis for a completely new implementation of LISP in a personal machine environment. The LISP machine, like other personal machines, has an integrated display, keyboard/mouse, and high bandwidth local network. In the light of the now familiar nature of these components, this talk concentrates on the design and architecture of the emulation engine, and the features which make it especially well suited for execution of compiled LISP. These include fast typed object dispatcher and hardware for assisting the Baker real time garbage collector algorithm.
  - The Transaction Concept: Virtues and Limitations, by Dr. James N. Gray., 1981-05-13; V0058.015; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 3)
    Transactions are transformations of state which have the properties of atomicity (all or nothing), durability (effects survive failures) and consistency (they implement the correct transformations). The transaction concept is key to the structuring of data management applications. The concept seems to have applicability to programming systems in general. This talk restates the transaction concepts and attempts to put several implementation approaches in perspective. It then describes some areas which require further study: (1) the integration of the transaction concept with the notion of abstract data type, (2) some techniques to allow transactions to be composed of subtransactions, and (3) handling transactions which last for extremely long times (days or months).
  - A RISCy Approach to Microcomputer Technology, by Prof. David A. Patterson., 1981-05-17; V0058.016; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 3)
    The Reduced Instruction Set Computer (RISC) Project investigates an alternative to the general trend towards computers with increasingly complex instruction sets. By a judicious choice of a proper set of instructions and the design of a corresponding architecture, one can obtain a machine with a high effective throughput. The simplicity of the instruction set and addressing modes allows most instructions to execute in a single machine cycle, and the simplicity of each instruction guarantees a short cycle time. In addition such a machine should have a much shorter design time. This computer is being implemented as part of a four quarter sequence of graduate courses in which students propose and evaluate architectural ideas, design VLSI components, integrate these components into a single chip, and finally test the chips that they have designed. We are nearing the end of the third phase. After presenting the architecture and our design aids, we describe how the goal of the project evolved to building a computer the size of a Motorola 68000 microprocessor with the performance of a V AX 11 minicomputer.
  - The Polycyclic Architecture, by Dr. B.R. Rau., 1981-11-18; V0058.017; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 3)
    A horizontal architecture uses a wide instruction word to simultaneously control multiple resources. Such architectures offer the potential for high performance scientific computing at a modest cost. If this potential performance is to be realized the multiple resources of a horizontal processor must be scheduled effectively. The scheduling task for conventional horizontal processors is quite complex and the construction of highly optimized compilers for them is a difficult and expensive project. The polycyclic architecture is a horizontal architecture with support for the task scheduling by using delay elements (storage embedded within the interconnection scheme).
  - Translation Buffer Performance in the V AX-lII780, by Dr. Douglas Clark., 1982-11-10; V0058.018; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 3)
    The V AX Translation Buffer (TB) is a cache of recently used virtual-to-physical address translations. In this talk Dr. Clark presents the results of some measurements of the TB in a VAX -111780. The measurements were made with a hardware monitor and the VAX was measured during ordinary timesharing use as well as under a reproducible synthetic workload. Results include the miss ratio of the TB for both Process space and System space, the TB-flushing context switch frequency, and the amount of time spent servicing TB misses. Additional measurements were made with half the TB disabled.
  - PSL: A Portable LISP System, by Prof. Martin L. Griss., 1983-01-26; V0058.019; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 3)
    PSL is a new portable implementation of LISP, based on the earlier Standard LISP systems from Utah. The system is distinguished by having essentially all of the interpreter and compiler written in PSL itself, compiled by an optimizing compiler. PSL runs on the DEC System 20, the VAX under UNIX, and a variety of Motorola 68000 based systems. Implementations for the CRA Y -1 and IBM-370 are underway. The talk describes the design philosophy and current status of PSL.
  - VISION TM, A Multi-Window Operating Environment for Personal Computers, by William T. Coleman., 1983-03-02; V0058.020; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 4)
    VisiON is a multi-window operating environment which uses a mouse pointing device. It has been developed so as to be highly portable across personal computers. The system will be demonstrated on the IBM Personal Computer, followed by an overview of the design objectives and the design of the system.
  - Life at Ground Zero, by Dr. Peter Stoll., 1983-03-30; V0058.021; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 4)
    The design of integrated circuits is not yet a stable art, let alone a science. The explosion in scale of the designs changes the very nature of the design problem. Even at the electrical performance level, formerly negligible problem such as lead inductance assume importance. Advantages in many areas argue for the comprehensive use of CMOS for new logic circuit designs.
  - Hierarchical Digital Design Methods, by Dr. Glen G. Langdon., 1983-04-13; V0058.022; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 4)
    A hierarchical digital design method which has been used in practice and in teaching a course in computer design will be presented. A relatively simple computer CPU presents an interesting level of complexity which filters out design techniques which "run out of steam" in complex digital systems. The course requires a "paper design: project of a CPU with an 10 bus, interrupt system, indirect addressing, and a studentarchitected subroutine call. The project motivates the student to reduce the complexity of herlhis task by learning a systematic hierarchical approach. Hierarchical levels of a Computer System are described. Digital design deals with three conceptual levels: (1) the instruction set architecture, (2) the functional units of the data flow, and (3) the basic gates and flip-flops. Hierarchical design bridges these conceptual gaps using a combination of strategies: top-down (divide-and-conquer) and bottom-up (construct more powerful functional units). Design is an interactive process, at each level the most important problem is attacked first and the detail is postponed. As the important decisions are made, and the detail is filled in at a lower level, it is usually necessary to modify the design. The data flowlcontrol unit level, the data part and control unit part are treated separately. The data flow involves bussing, registers, and functional units such as MUXs (assemblers), ALUs and shifters. Concurrences classes within the data flow add to the performance. The control unit determines the behavior of the system by sequencing the data flow operations. An important third component to design at this level is the system timing A two-dimensional (2nd level) diagram is advantageous to describe the data flow. A sequence of micro operations (register-transfer statements) is convenient to describe the control flow. System timing is best described with timing charts.
  - Digital Printing and Typesetting, by Prof. Brian K. Reid., 1983-06-01; V0058.023; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 4)
    Display technology has advanced significantly in recent years; it is now easy to build a workstation with a 1000 by 1000 color display. The technologies for printing those images on paper are significantly less advanced. I [with] begin a quick outline of the various technologies for making printed images and the way that they are currently used. These devices can be uneasily classified into three categories: plotters, typesetters, and laser printers. I explain how each such device works and what its limitations are. The future of printing technology clearly belongs to raster technologies. Raster Plotters such as the Versatec, raster typesetters such as the Alphatype, and raster laser printers such as the Canon have been available for some years, but technologies are developing that will permit laser printing devices, explaining their construction, operation, and control. I conclude with a brief description of the Stanford "Folio" laser printer project, which is the design of an ultrahigh-speed laser printer controller for use with the SUN workstation.
  - Machines Who Learn, by Prof. Douglas B. Lenat., 1983-11-15; V0058.024; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 4)
    The major bottleneck in building large AI programs is knowledge acquisition, and one way of widening that is by having the program learn new knowledge automatically. There has been an explosion of interest and activity in machine learning in the past few years. This talk focuses on my own efforts over the past decade to build machines who learn by discovery, guided by a large body of informal heuristic rules. Some of these rules suggest plausible concepts to consider at each moment, some evaluate candidates for interestingness. The domains in which our latest program, EURISKO, explores are quite diverse: set theory, number theory, plumbing, naval ship design, and the design of three-dimensional VLSI circuits. Many of our results are exciting and some are quite humorous.
  - Machines Who See and Do, by Prof. Rodney A. Brooks., 1983-11-22; V0058.025; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 4)
    Biological evolution has produced many animals capable of various levels of vision, mobility and manipulative skill. How can we give robots the same abilities? This talk overviews three examples of robot programs in model-based vision, 3-d path planning, and assembly plan checking, and shows a common methodology linking them. In each case a continuous class of possibilities is assumed while a physical process or event is modeled and then "run backwards" to solve the perceptual or planning problem
  - The MIPS Project, by Christopher Rowen., 1983-11-16; V0058.026; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 5)
    VLSI technology provides new constraints and challenges for computer architects. Silicon can provide low cost and high performance only if the hardware resources of the machine are carefully chosen and heavily used. The MIPS project at Stanford explores the interaction of VLSI with new architectural ideas. Like the Berkeley RISC and IBM 801 projects, MIPS uses a streamlined instruction set. Its heavily pipelined micro architecture ensures high utilization of silicon resources. It relies on advanced compiler technology to shift much complexity of hardware into software. Our nMOS VLSI implementation capitalizes on the natural regularity of the architecture to create a working processor several times the speed of commercial microprocessors. This talk describes the architecture and implementation of MIPS.
  - Software Army on the March -Project Strategies and Tactics, by Dr. John R. Mashey., 1983-09-28; V0058.027; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 5)
    This talk describes the work of an army building roads as an analogy to software projects. Decision-making processes are examined from two different viewpoints. The first is the formal game theory viewpoint - making decisions in a non- deterministic, multi-stage, non-zero-sum game played with incomplete information. The second is the "army" model. From this viewpoint are discussed such issues as fighting the right war in the first place and choosing good routes to reach the goals; the need for scouts on motorcycles ("fast prototypers"); how campaigns differ, and thus affect the choice of troops; special precautions for earthquake country; getting natives to buy and drive your trucks, instead of shooting your tires out as you drive through their villages. There exist many similarities in the decision processes of formal game analysis, military planning, and project management. The talk uses the first and second to help shed light on the third.
  - Modula-2, by Prof. Niklaus Wirth., 1983-10-04; V0058.028; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 5)
    Modula-2 is a high-level programming language, coming after Pascal and Algol, which has been in use since 1979. The whole program is a module, which justifies the name of the language. One of the most useful aspects of Modula-2 is the concept of local objects which can be hidden but made to reappear. Modula-2 has greater capabilities than Pascal in its more regular syntax, procedure variables, and low-level programming abilities. Professor Wirth also discusses the powerful and versatile compiler he built in conjunction with the development of Modula-2.
  - Etherphone-Ethernet Voice Service, by Dr. Lawrence C. Stewart., 1983-12-07; V0058.029; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 5)
    This talk describes the architecture and initial implementation of an experimental telephone system developed by the Computer Science Laboratory at the Xerox Palo Alto Research Center. A specially designed processor (Etherphone) connects to a telephone instrument and transmits digitized voice, signally, and supervisory information in discrete packets over the Ethernet local area network. When used by itself, an Etherphone provides the functions2 of a conventional telephone, but it comes into its own when combined with the capabilities of a nearby office workstation, a voice file service, and other shared services such as databases. Most of the work so far has gone into the basic provisions for voice switching and transmission. Today the system supports ordinary telephone calls and simple voice message services. These functions will be expanded as more is learned about the integration of voice with experimental office systems.
  - The Bagel: A Systolic Concurrent Prolog Machine, by Prof. Ehud Shapiro., 1984-01-04; V0058.030; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 5)